<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
 <!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
 <!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-http-source-information-header-kisteleki-levy-01" ipr="trust200902">
 <front>
   <title abbrev="HTTP Server-ID">HTTP Server-ID header for determining specific anycast instance</title>

   <author fullname="Robert Kisteleki" initials="R." surname="Kisteleki">
     <organization>RIPE NCC</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>Singel 258</street>
         <city>Amsterdam</city>
         <region></region>
         <code>1016 AB</code>
         <country>NL</country>
       </postal>
       <phone>+33 20 535 44 44</phone>
       <email>robert@ripe.net</email>
     </address>
   </author>
   <author fullname="Martin J. Levy" initials="M.J." surname="Levy">
     <organization>CloudFlare, Inc.</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>101 Townsend Street</street>
         <city>San Francisco</city>
         <region>California</region>
         <code>94107</code>
         <country>US</country>
       </postal>
       <phone>+1 650 319 8939</phone>
       <email>martin@cloudflare.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <date year="2016" />

   <area>General</area>

   <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

   <keyword>HTTP Header</keyword>

   <abstract>
     <t>
This document proposes a new HTTP header field, similar to NSID for DNS
queries, to add an optional identifier to the HTTP server generating the
response to a request. Such a header could be used to identifier which
location or server instance was reached by the user, which can be useful in
anycast deployments and CDNs.
     </t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>

   <section title="Introduction">

     <t>
We propose to add an OPTIONAL HTTP header, X-Server-ID. The value of such a
filed is determined by the server operator; this document does not specify
syntactical or semantic constraints.
     </t>

     <t>
The specific use-case would be to specify the identity of the server and maybe
it's geographic location.
     </t>

     <t>
While it's not normally important to know where HTTP data is being delivered
from; it can be a useful debugging tool to have that information kept in the HTTPheader.
Normally, lower level protocols can be used (traceroute, ping, etc.) to determine the
source end point location. With this header, the data would be there by default wihin
every transaction.
     </t>

     <t>
Front-end load-balancers can also mask the specific server delivering data. This
is sometimes the desired operational mode. In some cases, for debugging reasons, it's
useful to know the actual source server.
     </t>

     <t>
The source IP address within an HTTP transaction normally can be mapped to a
geographic location when Unicast addressesing is used. Anycast services change that
dynamic.
     </t>

     <t>
As more and more web services are delivered from Anycast servers; it becomes
harder to know which physical location information is being delivered from.
     </t>

     <section title="Requirements Language">
       <t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
"SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.
       </t>
     </section>

    </section>

    <section title="The Header blah blah">
     <t>
We propose to add an OPTIONAL HTTP header, X-Server-ID. The value of such a
filed is determined by the server operator; this document SHALL NOT specify
syntactical or semantic constraints. However, operators SHOULD use values
that can help clients to interpret the value itself, such as geolocation
codes (UNLOC, <xref target="IATA">IATA codes</xref>, POP identifiers, etc.)
in combination with some kind of server instances identifiers.

The length of the value for this header cannot be more than 4 kilobytes (?)

*To be checked: can multiple instances of the same header appear? If yes,
say so. If not, then make the value a pussible list, with ";" as separator.
     </t>
   </section>

   <section title="Examples">
     <t>
The X-Server-ID header contents can be as simple as the <xref target="IATA">IATA
code</xref> for the airport closest to the servers location. IATA codes are commonly
used within the Internet for names of sites and links.
     </t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="header-example-1">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
+-----------------------+
| X-Server-ID: JFK      |
+-----------------------+ ]]></artwork>
        <postamble>An X-Server-ID header showing the local airport code.</postamble>
      </figure>

     <t>
More complex examples could include specific server information along with
location.
     </t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="header-example-2">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
+---------------------------------------+
| X-Server-ID: 2334677359553192-SIN     |
+---------------------------------------+ ]]></artwork>
        <postamble>An X-Server-ID header showing company specific informaiton along with locations.</postamble>
      </figure>

     <t>
The X-Server-ID header data SHOULD try not to duplicate the work of existing headers.
For example; not replicating the X-Powered-By or Server header informaiton.
     </t>

   </section>

    <section title="Recursion">
     <t>
There needs to be a way to address recursion when HTTP headers and content
pass thru proxies or caches. As HTTP header names MUST be unique and only
occure once, any additional server wanting to add content to the X-Server-ID
header MUST do so in an additive manner.
     </t>

      <figure align="center" anchor="header-before-recursion">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
+-----------------------+
| X-Server-ID: JFK      |
+-----------------------+ ]]></artwork>
        <postamble>An X-Server-ID header before a proxy or cache.</postamble>
      </figure>

      <figure align="center" anchor="header-after-recursion">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
+-----------------------+
| X-Server-ID: JFK,EWR  |
+-----------------------+ ]]></artwork>
        <postamble>An X-Server-ID header after a proxy or cache.</postamble>
      </figure>

     <t>
As this document SHALL NOT specify syntactical or semantic constraints of the
headers value, the choice of comma is up to the implementer.
     </t>

   </section>

    <section title="The Via Header">
     <t>
The <xref target="Via-Header">Via Header</xref> was introduced to detect loops
when proxies or caches are used within the HTTP path. The proposed X-Server-ID
header works independently from that header and doesn't change it's usefullness
or functionality.
     </t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
     <t>
This work was propted by the work of the <xref target="Atlas">RIPE Atlas</xref>
project and it's need to indentify HTTP servers when they are Anycast.
In addition, this work is based on the existing CF- HTTP header used within
<xref target="CloudFlare">CloudFlare's Anycast CDN deployment</xref>.
     </t>

     <t>
This document is in-part a generalization and specification  of already existing
company-specific solutions.
     </t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
     <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>
   </section>

   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
     <t>
This header, by its very nature, exposes the existence of web servers or
co-location sites or both. Server operators who are concerned abot this
exposure should not opt in to this feature.

NOTE: technically speaking, the "Server" header could be abused. As of now,
this should say "Apache 2.2.x" or such, but it could say "Apache 2.2.x @
LAX-2" as well. I'm arguing that this would be an overload, though it's a
simple one to tweak...
     </t>
   </section>

 </middle>

 <back>
   <references title="Normative References">
     <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->
     &RFC2119;

     <reference anchor="IATA" target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_airports_by_IATA_code">
       <front>
         <title>List of airports by IATA code/</title>
         <author>
           <organization>Wikipedia</organization>
         </author>
         <date year="2016" />
       </front>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="Via-Header" target="https://blog.cloudflare.com/preventing-malicious-request-loops/">
       <front>
         <title>Preventing Malicious Request Loops/</title>
         <author fullname="Nick Sullivan" initials="N.S." surname="Sullivan">
           <organization>CloudFlare</organization>
         </author>
         <date year="2016" />
       </front>
     </reference>

   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">
     &RFC3552;

     <reference anchor="Atlas" target="https://atlas.ripe.net/">
       <front>
         <title>RIPE Atlas project</title>
         <author>
           <organization>RIPE NCC</organization>
         </author>
         <date year="2016" />
       </front>
     </reference>

     <reference anchor="CloudFlare" target="https://cloudflare.com/">
       <front>
         <title>CloudFlare, Inc.</title>
         <author>
           <organization>CloudFlare, Inc.</organization>
         </author>
         <date year="2016" />
       </front>
     </reference>

   </references>

   <section anchor="app-additional" title="Additional Stuff">
     <t>This becomes an Appendix.</t>
   </section>

   <!-- Change Log
v00 2016-02-07  RK    Initial text
v01 2016-02-14  MJL   Initial xml draft version
    -->

 </back>
</rfc>
